increased heart rate, sweating of the skin. Whilst the psychopaths in our study were able to describe the pictures accurately, they failed to show the emotions required. They failed to show a physical response. It was as though they knew the words but not the music of empathy. So we wanted to look closer at this to use MRI to image their brains. That turned out to be not such an easy task. Imagine transporting a collection of clinical psychopaths across central London in shackles and handcuffs in rush hour, and in order to place each of them in an MRI scanner, you have to remove all metal objects, including shackles and handcuffs, and, as I learned, all body piercings. After some time, however, we had a tentative answer. These individuals were not just the victims of a troubled childhood. There was something else. People like Joe have a deficit in a brain area called the amygdala. The amygdala is an almond-shaped organ deep within each of the hemispheres of the brain. It is thought to be key to the experience of empathy. Normally, the more empathic a person is, the larger and more active their amygdala is. Our population of inmates had a deficient amygdala, which likely led to their lack of empathy and to their immoral behavior. So let's take a step back. Normally, acquiring moral behavior is simply part of growing up, like learning to speak. At the age of six months, virtually every one of us is able to differentiate between animate and inanimate objects. At the age of 12 months, most children are able to imitate the purposeful actions of others. So for example, your mother raises her hands to stretch, and you imitate her behavior. At first, this isn't perfect. I remember my cousin Sasha, two years old at the time, looking through a picture book and licking one finger and flicking the page with the other hand, licking one finger and flicking the page with the other hand. (Laughter) Bit by bit, we build the foundations of the social brain so that by the time we're three, four years old, most children, not all, have acquired the ability to understand the intentions of others, another prerequisite for empathy. The fact that this developmental progression is universal, irrespective of where you live in the world or which culture you inhabit, strongly suggests that the foundations of moral behavior are inborn. If you doubt this, try, as I've done, to renege on a promise you've made to a four-year-old. You will find that the mind of a four-year old is not naïve in the slightest. It is more akin to a Swiss army knife with fixed mental modules finely honed during development and a sharp sense of fairness. The early years are crucial. There seems to be a window of opportunity, after which mastering moral questions becomes more difficult, like adults learning a foreign language. That's not to say it's impossible. A recent, wonderful study from Stanford University showed that people who have played a virtual reality game in which they took on the role of a good and helpful superhero actually became more caring and helpful towards others afterwards. Now I'm not suggesting we endow criminals with superpowers, but I am suggesting that we need to find ways to get Joe and people like him to change their brains and their behavior, for their benefit and for the benefit of the rest of us. So can brains change? For over 100 years, neuroanatomists and later neuroscientists held the view that after initial development in childhood, no new brain cells could grow in the adult human brain. The brain could only change within certain set limits. That was the dogma. But then, in the 1990s, studies starting showing, following the lead of Elizabeth Gould at Princeton and others, studies started showing the evidence of neurogenesis, the birth of new brain cells in the adult mammalian brain, first in the olfactory bulb, which is responsible for our sense of smell, then in the hippocampus involving short-term memory, and finally in the amygdala itself. In order to understand how this process works, I left the psychopaths and joined a lab in Oxford specializing in learning and development. Instead of psychopaths, I studied mice, because the same pattern of brain responses appears across many different species of social animals. So if you rear a mouse in a standard cage, a shoebox, essentially, with cotton wool, alone and without much stimulation, not only does it not thrive, but it will often develop strange, repetitive behaviors. This naturally sociable animal will lose its ability to bond with other mice, even becoming aggressive when introduced to them. However, mice reared in what we called an enriched environment, a large habitation with other mice with wheels and ladders and areas to explore, demonstrate neurogenesis, the birth of new brain cells, and as we showed, they also perform better on a range of learning and memory tasks. Now, they don't develop morality to the point of carrying the shopping bags of little old mice across the street, but their improved environment results in healthy, sociable behavior. Mice reared in a standard cage, by contrast, not dissimilar, you might say, from a prison cell, have dramatically lower levels of new neurons in the brain. It is now clear that the amygdala of mammals, including primates like us, can show neurogenesis. In some areas of the brain, more than 20 percent of cells are newly formed. We're just beginning to understand what exact function these cells have, but what it implies is that the brain is capable of extraordinary change way into adulthood. However, our brains are also exquisitely sensitive to stress in our environment. Stress hormones, glucocorticoids, released by the brain, suppress the growth of these new cells. The more stress, the less brain development, which in turn causes less adaptability and causes higher stress levels. This is the interplay between nature and nurture in real time in front of our eyes. When you think about it, it is ironic that our current solution for people with stressed amygdalae is to place them in an environment that actually inhibits any chance of further growth. Of course, imprisonment is a necessary part of the criminal justice system and of protecting society. Our research does not suggest that criminals should submit their MRI scans as evidence in court and get off the hook because they've got a faulty amygdala. The evidence is actually the other way. Because our brains are capable of change, we need to take responsibility for our actions, and they need to take responsibility for their rehabilitation. One way such rehabilitation might work is through restorative justice programs. Here victims, if they choose to participate, and perpetrators meet face to face in safe, structured encounters, and the perpetrator is encouraged to take responsibility for their actions, and the victim plays an active role in the process. In such a setting, the perpetrator can see, perhaps for the first time, the victim as a real person with thoughts and feelings and a genuine emotional response. This stimulates the amygdala and may be a more effective rehabilitative practice than simple incarceration. Such programs won't work for everyone, but for many, it could be a way to break the frozen sea within. So what can we do now? How can we apply this knowledge? I'd like to leave you with three lessons that I learned. The first thing that I learned was that we need to change our mindset. Since Wormwood Scrubs was built 130 years ago, society has advanced in virtually every aspect, in the way we run our schools, our hospitals. Yet the moment we speak about prisons, it's as though we're back in Dickensian times, if not medieval times. For too long, I believe, we've allowed ourselves to be persuaded of the false notion that human nature cannot change, and as a society, it's costing us dearly. We know that the brain is capable of extraordinary change, and the best way to achieve that, even in adults, is to change and modulate our environment. The second thing I have learned is that we need to create an alliance of people who believe that science is integral to bringing about social change. It's easy enough for a neuroscientist to place a high-security inmate in an MRI scanner. Well actually, that turns out not to be so easy, but ultimately what we want to show is whether we're able to reduce the reoffending rates. In order to answer complex questions like that, we need people of different backgrounds -- lab-based scientists and clinicians, social workers and policy makers, philanthropists and human rights activists — to work together. Finally, I believe we need to change our own amygdalae, because this issue goes to the heart not just of who Joe is, but who we are. We need to change our view of Joe as someone wholly irredeemable, because if we see Joe as wholly irredeemable, how is he going to see himself as any different? In another decade, Joe will be released from Wormwood Scrubs. Will he be among the 70 percent of inmates who end up reoffending and returning to the prison system? Wouldn't it be better if, while serving his sentence, Joe was able to train his amygdala, which would stimulate the growth of new brain cells and connections, so that he will be able to face the world once he gets released? Surely, that would be in the interest of all of us. (Applause) Thank you. (Applause)
aumento de la frecuencia cardíaca, sudor en la piel... Aunque los psicópatas del estudio podían describir las imágenes con exactitud, no presentaban las emociones correspondientes. No presentaban una respuesta física. Era como si conociesen las palabras, pero no la música de la empatía. Queríamos analizar mejor esto y hacer resonancias magnéticas de sus cerebros. No resultó ser una tarea tan fácil. Imaginen transportar a un grupo de psicópatas por el centro de Londres con grilletes y esposas en hora pico, y para hacerles la resonancia había que quitarles todos los objetos metálicos, incluyendo esposas y grilletes, y, como descubrí, todo de las perforaciones del cuerpo. Sin embargo, tiempo después, obtuvimos una respuesta provisional. Esas personas no solo eran víctimas de una infancia problemática. Había algo más. La gente como Joe tenía una deficiencia en un área del cerebro llamada amígdala. La amígdala es un órgano con forma de almendra que está en la profundidad de cada hemisferio del cerebro. Se cree que es crucial para la empatía. Cuanto más empática es una persona, mayor y más activa es su amígdala. Nuestros internos tenían una amígdala deficiente, lo que probablemente causaba la falta de empatía y el comportamiento inmoral. Retrocedamos un momento. Normalmente, adquirimos comportamientos morales según maduramos, igual que como aprendemos a hablar. A los seis meses, casi todos nosotros podemos diferenciar entre objetos animados e inanimados. A los 12 meses, la mayoría de niños puede imitar acciones voluntarias de otros. Por ejemplo, tu madre levanta las manos para estirarse y tú la imitas. Al principio, no sale perfecto. Recuerdo a mi prima Sasha, cuando tenía dos años, hojeando un libro de cuentos, chupándose un dedo y pasando las páginas con la otra mano, chupándose un dedo y pasando las páginas con la otra mano. (Risas) Poco a poco, construimos las bases del cerebro social de modo que para los tres o cuatro años, casi todos los niños, no todos, han adquirido la capacidad de entender las intenciones de los otros, otro prerrequisito para la empatía. El hecho de que esta progresión del desarrollo sea universal, independiente de dónde vivamos o de cuál sea nuestra cultura, es un fuerte indicador de que las bases del comportamiento moral son innatas. Si lo dudan, intenten, como yo, romper una promesa que le hayan hecho a un niño de cuatro años. Verán que la mente de un niño de cuatro años no es ingenua en absoluto. Se parece más a una navaja suiza con módulos mentales fijos, pulidos finamente durante el crecimiento, y con un agudo sentido de la justicia. Los primeros años son cruciales. Parece haber un momento para ello, tras el cual dominar las cuestiones morales es más difícil, como a los adultos aprender un idioma. Pero no quiere decir que sea imposible. Hace poco, un maravilloso estudio de la Universidad de Stanford demostró que la gente que había jugado a un juego de realidad virtual en el que tomaban el rol de un superhéroe bueno y servicial se vuelvían más cariñosos y serviciales con los demás en el futuro. No estoy sugiriendo que le demos superpoderes a los criminales, sino que necesitamos encontrar formas para que Joe y gente como él cambien sus mentes y sus comportamientos, por su bien y por el de los demás. ¿Puede cambiar el cerebro? Por más de 100 años, los neuroanatomistas y los neurocientíficos argumentaban que después del desarrollo inicial en la infancia, no podían crecer nuevas neuronas en el cerebro adulto. El cerebro solo podía cambiar dentro de unos límites establecidos. Ese era el dogma. Pero en los años 90, algunos estudios empezaron a demostrar, siguiendo el camino de Elizabeth Gould en Princeton y de otros, que había pruebas de neurogénesis, del nacimiento de nuevas neuronas, en el cerebro mamífero adulto; primero en el bulbo olfativo, responsable del sentido del olfato, después en el hipocampo, que actuá en la memoria a corto plazo, y finalmente en la propia amígdala. Para entender cómo funciona este proceso, dejé a los psicópatas e ingresé a un laboratorio de Oxford para especializarme en aprendizaje y desarrollo. En lugar de psicópatas, estudiaba ratones, porque el mismo patrón de respuesta cerebral aparece en muchas especies de animales sociales. Si crías un ratón en una jaula común, en una caja de zapatos, con algodón, solo y sin muchos estímulos, no solo no se desarrolla bien, sino que a menudo aparecen comportamientos raros y repetitivos. Este animal sociable por naturaleza perderá su capacidad de relacionarse con otros ratones, e incluso se pondrá agresivo cuando se los pone con ellos. Pero los ratones criados en lo que llamamos un ambiente enriquecido, un habitáculo grande con otros ratones, con ruedas, escaleras y otras zonas para explorar, presentan neurogénesis, el nacimiento de nuevas neuronas, y, como demostramos, llevan a cabo mejor una serie de tareas de aprendizaje y memoria. Pero no desarrollan la moralidad hasta el punto de llevarle las bolsas por la calle a los ratones ancianitos, pero las mejores condiciones ambientales generan un comportamiento social saludable. Por el contrario, los ratones criados en jaulas comunes, no muy distintas, se podría decir, a la celda de una prisión, tienen niveles significativamente más bajos de neuronas nuevas. Queda claro que la amígdala de los mamíferos, incluyendo a los primates como nosotros, puede presentar neurogénesis. En algunas partes del cerebro, más del 20 % de las células son nuevas. Estamos apenas empezando a entender la función exacta de esas células, pero lo que implica es que el cerebro es capaz de cambios extraordinarios bien avanzada la vida adulta. Sin embargo, nuestro cerebro también es sumamente sensible al estrés que nos rodea. Las hormonas del estrés, la glucocorticoides, liberadas por el cerebro, suprime el crecimiento de estas células nuevas . Cuanto más estrés, menos desarrollo cerebral, lo que genera, a su vez, menos adaptabilidad y aumenta los niveles de estrés. Esta es la interacción entre naturaleza y crianza en tiempo real, delante de nuestros ojos. Cuando piensas en ello, resulta irónico que la solución actual para la gente con amígdalas estresadas sea ponerlas en un ambiente que en realidad inhibe toda posibilidad de crecimiento posterior. Por supuesto, el encarcelamiento es una parte necesaria en el sistema de la justicia penal para proteger a la sociedad. Nuestro estudio no sugiere que los criminales presenten sus resonancias como prueba en un juicio y se los libre porque no les funciona bien la amígdala. Las pruebas muestran que es al revés. Ya que nuestro cerebro puede cambiar, necesitamos ser responsables de nuestros actos y ellos tienen que hacerse responsables de rehabilitarse. Una forma en la que esa rehabilitación podría funcionar es a través de programas de justicia restaurativa. Aquí la víctima, si decide participar, y el criminal se ven cara a cara en encuentros seguros y estructurados, al criminal se le anima a responsabilizarse de sus actos, y la víctima tiene un papel activo en el proceso. En un encuentro así, el criminal puede ver, quizá por primera vez, a la víctima como a una persona real con pensamientos y sentimientos y una genuina respuesta emocional. Esto estimula la amígdala y puede ser una práctica de rehabilitación más efectiva que el simple encarcelamiento. Programas como este no funcionan para todos, pero para muchos, puede ser una forma de terminar con esa enorme frialdad interior. Entonces, ¿qué podemos hacer ahora? ¿Cómo aplicamos este conocimiento? Me gustaría dejarles tres lecciones que aprendí. Lo primero que aprendí fue que debemos cambiar nuestra mentalidad. Desde que se construyó Wormwood Scrubs hace 130 años, la sociedad ha avanzado en casi todos los aspectos, en la forma en que dirigimos nuestros colegios y hospitales. Aun así, cuando hablamos de prisiones es como si volviésemos a la época de Dickens o a la Edad Media. Por demasiado tiempo, creo, nos hemos permitido creer en la idea falsa de que la naturaleza humana no puede cambiar y, como sociedad, lo estamos pagando carísimo. Sabemos que el cerebro es capaz de cambios extraordinarios y la mejor forma de conseguirlo, incluso en adultos, es cambiar y modular nuestro ambiente. Lo segundo que aprendí es que necesitamos crear una unión entre la gente que cree que la ciencia es esencial para generar el cambio social. Es muy fácil para un neurocientífico hacerle una resonancia a un preso de alta seguridad. Pues bien, resulta que no es tan fácil, pero lo que en verdad queremos ver es si podemos reducir las tasas de reincidencia. Para responder preguntas tan complejas, necesitamos gente con diferentes formaciones: clínicos y científicos de laboratorio, políticos y trabajadores sociales, filántropos y defensores de los derechos humanos. Necesitamos que trabajen unidos. Finalmente, creo que necesitamos cambiar nuestras propias amígdalas, porque esta cuestión llega al fondo no solo de quién es Joe, sino de quiénes somos nosotros. Necesitamos dejar de ver a Joe como alguien totalmente incorregible, porque, si nosotros lo vemos así, ¿cómo va a hacer él para verse distinto? Dentro de una década, Joe será liberado de Wormwood Scrubs. ¿Estará entre el 70 % de internos que terminan reincidiendo y vuelven al sistema penitenciario? ¿No sería mejor que, mientras cumple condena, Joe entrenara su amígdala, lo que estimularía el crecimiento de nuevas células cerebrales y conexiones, para que, de ese modo, pueda enfrentarse al mundo cuando lo liberen? Sin duda, eso nos beneficiaría a todos. (Aplausos) Gracias.